<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>IDeA Lab @ UC Davis</title>
    <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://davisidealab.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>IDeA Lab @ UC Davis</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://davisidealab.github.io/media/logo_hubffc35ffdbaa41bbc0ff4aaae51619a3_31464_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url>
      <title>IDeA Lab @ UC Davis</title>
      <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Air pollution and noise exposures in relation to dementia: from brain imaging markers to clinical disease</title>
      <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag065359/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag065359/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ag065359&#34;&gt;AG065359&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burgeoning evidence suggests that exposure to air pollution may result in impaired cognitive function, cognitive decline, and increased risk of Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease and related dementias (ADRD). Newer, sparser evidence hints that these outcomes could also be influenced by ambient noise. If these environmental exposures do worsen cognition in older adults, they would be among the few pervasive risk factors for cognitive loss that can be modified on broad scale to benefit entire populations. Despite major implications for public health, there are critical limitations in our knowledge of how air pollution and noise affect neurocognitive aging. Most studies of these exposures in relation to ADRD have relied on medical or health administrative records, which provide strikingly unreliable data on dementia status. Both exposures increase cardiovascular risk. If health care use for these conditions makes it more likely that a person with dementia is diagnosed, then using medical records to estimate of the relation of air pollution and noise to ADRD risk could overestimate these associations. A second limitation is that the mechanisms by which these exposures promote cognitive deterioration are unclear, although cerebrovascular pathways have been proposed. Finally, air pollution and ambient noise often co-occur, yet few studies have been able to determine if these exposures amplify each other&amp;rsquo;s effects. To overcome these limitations and knowledge gaps, we propose to investigate the effects of air pollution and noise exposure on cognitive decline and ADRD and, using brain MRI measurements, to evaluate these exposures&#39; influence on cerebrovascular injury and neuronal death. We take advantage of 2 large, racially diverse population-based cohort studies of older adults, the Chicago Health and Aging Project (CHAP) and the Parent Offspring Resilience and Cognitive Health (PORCH) study. We will integrate data from cohort participants on cognitive decline, ADRD, and brain MRI with estimates of their long-term exposures to noise and air pollution from traffic, generated in ongoing collaboration with the MESA Air and ancillary projects. We will focus on traffic-related air pollution (TRAP), because traffic remains one of the most pervasive sources of air pollution exposure. This work extends our ongoing research by: investigating brain MRI measures of cerebrovascular injury; evaluating other constituents of TRAP, including the metals released from brake and tire wear; and evaluating the effects of TRAP and noise in combination. Our overarching hypothesis is that TRAP and noise exposures hasten cognitive decline, increase ADRD risk, and promote cerebrovascular ischemia and brain atrophy. We further hypothesize that TRAP and noise exposure together influence these outcomes, above and beyond what would be expected from their individual associations with these outcomes. Reductions in environmental pollutants have already benefited the population&amp;rsquo;s health. The data from this project may provide impetus—the prospect of reducing the population burden of ADRD—for further reductions and identify both air pollution and noise as targets for population-level strategies for ADRD prevention.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alzheimer&#39;s Disease Neuroimaging Initiative</title>
      <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag024904/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag024904/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ag024904&#34;&gt;AG024904&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to determine relationships among the clinical, cognitive, imaging, genetic and biochemical biomarker characteristics of the entire spectrum of Alzheimers disease (AD), as pathology evolves from normal aging to very mild symptoms, to mild cognitive impairment (MCI), to dementia. ADNl will inform the neuroscience of AD, identify diagnostic and prognostic markers, identify outcome measures that can be used in clinical trials, and help develop the most effective clinical trial scenarios. ADNI2 continues the currently funded AD Neuroimaging Initiative (ADNI1), a public/private collaboration between academia and industry to study biomarkers of AD as well as a recently funded Grand Opportunities grant that supplements ADNl goals and activities (GO). New aspects of ADNl include enrolling subjects with early MCI (EMCI), F18 amyloid imaging, and obtaining all clinical/cognitive, lumbar puncture CSF and plasma biomarker, and MRI/PET data on all subjects. The goals of this ADNl renewal will be accomplished by: 1) continuing annual clinical/cognitive/MRI follow up of the 476 normal controls and late MCI (LMCI) subjects previously enrolled in ADNI1; 2) following the 200 EMCI subjects enrolled in the GO ADNl grant; 3) additional enrollment of new healthy controls (n=150), EMCI (n=100 which adds to the 200 subjects enrolled in GO), LMCI (n=150), and AD (n=150) subjects; 4) performance of F18 amyloid PET (using F18 AV-45 from AVID, Inc.) on all new subjects enrolled in ADNI2, together with FDG PET, and to obtain a 2nd F18 amyloid PET on all remaining ADNI1, GO, and ADNI2 subjects 2 years after the baseline scan; 5) continue to obtain annual clinical/cognitive/blood draw/lumbar puncture for CSF, and MRI on all subjects. All collected data will be processed and analyzed by ADNl investigators including the Biostatistical Core, and made available to all qualified scientists in the world who request a password, without embargo. Hypotheses developed from current ADNl data will be replicated and new hypotheses tested, especially concerning EMCI and F18 amyloid imaging. ADNl spawned large multisite projects in other countries. No other large multisite study in the world addresses these complex issues with the sample size and statistical power of this application.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clinical, Imaging, and Pathological Studies in the Oldest Old: The 90&#43; Study</title>
      <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag021055/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag021055/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ag021055&#34;&gt;AG021055&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 90+ Study was initiated January 1, 2003 as a population-based sample of oldest-old survivors of the Leisure World Cohort Study (LWCS, enrollment 1981-1984). With more than 1,800 participants, The 90+ Study is one of the largest and longest studies in the world of dementia, cognitive decline, disability, and frailty in the oldest-old. People over 90 are the fastest segment of the population and have the greatest public health impact as the risk of dementia is extraordinarily high in these individuals, reaching a staggering 40% per year in centenarians. However, many oldest old maintain superior cognitive performance well into their tenth decade and beyond (cognitive resilience), often in the presence of neuropathological changes (cognitive resilience in the presence of pathology). Lifestyle, co-morbid conditions, genetics, and other factors have been implicated in this cognitive resilience, but have not been well studied. In this application, we extend our studies to investigate cognitive resilience in these remarkable individuals. In Aim 1, we consider early (30 years earlier in the LWCS) and late (at age 90+) lifestyle and other factors in relation to cognitive resilience. Factors related to the maintenance of superior cognitive abilities in the presence of pathology are investigated in Aim 2. Taking advantage of our large cohort of 90+ year-olds in our imaging studies, we prospectively follow individuals without dementia to estimate incidence of dementia and rates of cognitive decline in relation to MRI and PET biomarkers in Aim 3. We analyze the role of low levels of multiple neuropathologic changes in the expression of dementia in Aim 4. Finally, with this application, we will recruit the last living LWCS participants eligible for our study, and complete ascertainment of all previously established outcomes in The 90+ Study (dementia, CIND, MCI, frailty, disability, and mortality). We will make this dataset spanning almost four decades publically available to the research community (Aim5). With our extensive database, unique large cohort of well-characterized individuals, extensive and multidisciplinary longitudinal follow-up, and innovative neuropathological and neuroimaging investigations, we are ideally positioned to do studies of dementia and resilience in the oldest-old. Identifying factors related to cognitive resilience and dementia, including modifiable lifestyle factors and imaging biomarkers, would contribute to our understanding of aging in health and disease and provide potential targets for interventions to promote successful aging.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Vascular Contributions to Dementia Risk in African-Americans</title>
      <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag050782/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag050782/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ag050782&#34;&gt;AG050782&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aims of this study are highly relevant for public health because we will delineate the long-term impact of lifecourse experience, and vascular contributions to cognitive impairment and brain pathology in African American individuals whom at a population level are at higher risk for dementia and Alzheimer’s disease. Findings will inform whether early life exposures, lifecourse social context, midlife vascular risk, and an increased burden of vascular comorbidities impacts cognitive decline, brain atrophy and brain vascular pathology. Results will directly benefit a vulnerable and understudied population which bears a tremendous burden of cognitive decline and at the same time is rapidly increasing. Results will have direct implications for potential prevention of cognitive impairment and Alzheimer’s disease in the African American population.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epidemiology of Age-related Dementia, Mild Cognitive Impairment and Brain Pathology in a Multiethnic Cohort of Oldest-Old</title>
      <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag056519/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag056519/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ag056519&#34;&gt;AG056519&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2050 there will be 8.5 million individuals aged 90+ in the US yet very little is known about brain aging beyond age 90 in ethnic minorities nor the role of early life influences on risk of very late-onset dementia. The Kaiser multiphasic study participants age 90+ offer an unprecedented and fleeting opportunity to evaluate 50 years of information and understand the lifecourse story of dementia and brain aging in a racially diverse oldest-old cohort. This study will redefine our knowledge of dementia and brain pathology in the oldest-old, provide new insights into early life risk and protective factors, uncover etiological underpinnings, and provide a framework for future studies of prevention of late-onset dementia and cognitive impairment in a multiethnic cohort.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lifecourse health, cerebral pathology and ethnic disparities in dementia</title>
      <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag052132/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag052132/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ag052132&#34;&gt;AG052132&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2012 President Obama signed the National Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Plan Act with a primary objective to decrease racial disparities of dementia. While it is known that certain ethnoracial groups such as Blacks have higher rates of dementia, reasons for these disparities are unknown. We propose an unprecedented lifecourse study of ethnic disparities in late life cognitive outcomes using a large multi-ethnic sample with over 5 decades of prospectively collected life history and health data. Our overall objectives are to delineate why there are racial/ethnic disparities in dementia and how risk and protective factors and brain mechanisms differ across ethnoracial groups.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microglial, Inflammatory and Omics Markers of Cerebral Small Vessel Disease in the CHARGE Consortium</title>
      <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ns100605/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ns100605/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ns100605&#34;&gt;NS100605&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cerebral Small Vessel Disease (SVD) is an important, potentially modifiable factor for clinical dementia. Recent data suggest that the age-specific incidence of dementia may be decreasing, partly as a result of better management of vascular risk factors, lending urgency to dementia prevention trials but a major impediment is the absence of circulating biomarkers for tracking onset and progression of SVD. Brain MRI imaging markers are the current gold standard for SVD but are too expensive and burdensome for repeated assessments. Recent genetic studies, including from the Cohorts for Heart &amp;amp; Aging Research in Genomic Epidemiology (CHARGE) consortium, implicate microglial inflammation and astroglia in the biology of SVD and dementia. We propose to measure 2 circulating biomarkers of microglial inflammation (sCD-14 and YKL-40) and a marker of astroglial injury (GFAP) in ~17,000 persons (including 4000 minority participants, 6000 with &amp;gt;2 MRI) across 5 CHARGE population-based cohorts. Specifcally, we will (1) examine the association of the novel biomarkers with (a) previously collected MRI-defined SVD (white matter hyperintensities, lacunar infarcts and cerebral microbleeds), and in persons under age 70, sensitive MRI measures of early, preclinical SVD such as fractional anisotropy on diffusion- weighted imaging, regional cortical thinning and perivascular spaces; (b) previously collected measures of cognitive function; and (c) neurocognitive and vascular consequences of SVD (dementia and stroke). We will use a Mendelian Randomization framework and existing genetic data to examine causal relationships between the novel biomarkers and MRI, neurocognitive, and clinical outcomes. (2) We will assess the incremental predictive utility of the novel biomarkers over (a) vascular risk factor profiles such as the Framingham Stroke Risk Prediction score; (b) over a panel of previously measured &amp;lsquo;candidate&amp;rsquo; biomarkers for SVD including CRP, IL6, TNF-alpha, fibrinogen, BNP, urine albumin, tHcy, ST2, GDF15, TnI, BDNF, VEGF, MMP-9, beta-amyloid, clusterin and APOE and (c) we will identify a parsimonious set of biomarkers that best predict presence of SVD and risk of cognitive decline, stroke and dementia. In summary we propose to leverage extensive available data to identify and validate a novel circulating biomarker profile of glial cell dysfunction that will improve our understanding of SVD biology and help in the prediction of SVD and its associated adverse neurological outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MRI Measures of Cerebrovascular Injury and AD Atrophy in a Study of Latinos</title>
      <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag054548/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag054548/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ag054548&#34;&gt;AG054548&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By leveraging the Hispanic Community Health Study/Study of Latinos (HCHS/SOL) cohort, we plan to examine the impact of disparities in vascular risk factors on brain health utilizing cutting edge MRI techniques within a large, understudied population of diverse Latinos spanning the age range of risk for stroke and dementia. We will also characterize the biological substrates of stroke, MCI and AD among the various racial admixtures in this deeply phenotyped cohort.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neuroscience of Cognitive Aging</title>
      <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag050061/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag050061/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ag050061&#34;&gt;AG050061&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern neuroscience has the potential to significantly contribute to meeting current and future social challenges related to the advancing age of the population. In order to maintain health and autonomy in old age, understanding of the basic mechanisms of aging processes are of the utmost urgency. Deciphering the changes in neural structure and function of the healthy brain throughout the entire life span is essential for developing new approaches for diagnostics, prevention, therapy and health care. Based on newly acquired knowledge about the basic mechanisms of aging appropriate training measures and interventions can be developed. As a consequence, the need for the infusion of new and highly creative young scientists into this area of research has never been more acute. The aim of this T32 training application, therefore, is to develop a highly diverse, but integrated program of neuroscience research that aims to understand the biological underpinnings of the aging brain as it relates to cognition across the spectrum of human brain aging. To accomplish this goal, we propose to bring together the outstanding neuroscience research and education resources of UC Davis in a synergistic and collaborative manner to train new post-doctoral students (3 per year - 3-year training programs, total of 6 trainees over 5 years). These trainees will serve as catalysts for translational neuroscience research on cognitive aging, and this program will bring added value to the UC Davis aging research community by bringing together disparate but complimentary faculty and laboratories and generating newly funded research related to advancing science to improve human health.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Novel imaging and endothelial biomarkers of small vessel cerebrovascular disease</title>
      <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ns100608/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ns100608/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ns100608&#34;&gt;NS100608&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Small vessel cerebrovascular disease and Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease are the two most common causes of cognitive decline in the elderly, but methods for determining the relative contributions of both these pathologies to functional impairment, understanding their interactions, predicting progression and defining targets for clinical trials remain underdeveloped. The overarching goal of this proposal is to further develop novel neuroimaging and serologic biomarkers of cerebrovascular disease. Accomplishing this goal will improve early detection, diagnosis, and prognosis of small vessel cerebrovascular disease in older subjects, and provide better targets and outcome metrics for clinical trials. We propose to longitudinally study 400 well characterized older subjects from ongoing projects at UCSF and UCD who present with a range of cerebrovascular burden and functional decline. Our search for biomarkers will focus on novel neuroimaging variables and measures of endothelial dysfunction. Our aims will address the relationships between these markers and measures of amyloid burden, cognition, and change over time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preserving Cognitive Resilience: A Biracial Parent-Offspring Study</title>
      <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag058679/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag058679/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ag058679&#34;&gt;AG058679&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed intergenerational research study would increase our understanding of cognitive resilience in late-life older adults, and examines the relation of midlife biomarkers of brain and cardiovascular health in offspring and cognitive resilience in parent. Preserving cognitive resilience through early, mid, and late life biomarkers is a topic of high public health significance, since designing of preventive strategies through life course can offer stronger potential for slowing or reducing the risk of developing cognitive loss in late-life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SCAN: Standardized Centralized Alzheimer&#39;s and Related Dementias Neuroimaging</title>
      <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag067418/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag067418/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ag067418&#34;&gt;AG067418&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overall goal of this application is to create an infrastructure for supporting and augmenting neuroimaging research in the National Institute of Aging’s Alzheimer’s Disease Centers (ADC) Program. The ADC program is comprised of 30 centers that pursue research goals dedicated to increasing our understanding of Alzheimer’s disease (AD) with a view towards improving diagnosis, care, and treatment of patients. Over the past decade, neuroimaging has played an increasingly important role in this mission, as new approaches to measuring brain structure, function, and biochemistry have produced biomarkers useful in diagnostic, mechanistic, and therapeutic studies. At the same time, methods for standardization of neuroimaging have become accepted, such that, despite the complexity and cost of imaging, we have the ability to combine images obtained at different centers in order to answer important questions about AD that require large datasets. This project will focus on standardizing approaches to magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and positron emission tomography (PET) images. MR standardization will address structural and functional (task-free) MRI, and PET standardization will address amyloid, tau, and glucose metabolic imaging. We will work with the National Alzheimer’s Coordinating Center (NACC) to develop protocols for securely uploading and de-identifying all images at a NACC image repository, where a searchable database will also be available to researchers. We will develop standards for MR and PET image acquisition, and make these imaging protocols available to the ADC community. Uploaded images will undergo rigorous quality control and processing to permit merging of images obtained on different platforms and, for PET, at different resolutions. Laboratories that have specialized in image processing will produce numerical summary data of brain cerebrovascular pathology, brain volumes, perfusion, diffusion, and cortical thickness, amyloid and tau deposition, and glucose metabolism. These numerical variables will be stored at NACC where it will be linked to other ADC-related data on participants and made available to researchers. Additional aspects of the program will include a website with documentation, search functions, and user help functions. The administrative structure of the project will involve an executive committee with membership from the participating laboratories as well as representation from the NACC, the ADCs, and NIA. Leadership will remain apprised of changes in the neuroimaging landscape, and incorporate new MR and PET measures as they develop with the overall goal of standardizing and disseminating agreed- upon best practices while not stifling the development of new, innovative technical advances.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Study of Latinos Investigation of Neurocognitive Aging 2</title>
      <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag048642/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag048642/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ag048642&#34;&gt;AG048642&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2060, the CDC projects that the Latino population will experience the largest increase in Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease and related dementia (ADRD) cases of all US ethnic/racial groups. The main, if not only, explanation oft echoed for disparately high Latino ADRD is attributed to early and excess cardiovascular disease (CVD) morbidity contributing to disparately high ADRD. CVD risk factors emerge earlier among Latinos in midlife, thereby increasing deleterious exposures to exquisitely sensitive and highly vascularized brain tissue. Yet, to- date there has not been any study of Latinos with sufficiently deep CVD phenotyping and genotyping to adequately address this significant public health question. This scientific knowledge gap is a significant impediment to the field and public health given continued and rapid Latino population growth projections, particularly for older adults. Latinos now represent nearly one-fifth of the US and 40% of its two most populous states, California and Texas. In coming decades, the older Latino population (&amp;gt;65 years) will quadruple (391%) and US public health is ill-prepared for forthcoming demographic and health-related shifts in the population. The Study of Latinos-Investigation of Neurocognitive Aging (SOL-INCA) is the only large, representative and ongoing longitudinal study of CVD, genomics and cognitive aging and ADRD in diverse Latinos. In this SOL- INCA renewal, we will leverage 10-years of deep CVD phenotyping, multi-layered -omics and rich sociocultural data to fill these neglected scientific gaps in our current understanding of ADRD in diverse Latinos.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temporal Trends, Novel Imaging and Molecular Characterization of Preclinical and Clinical Alzheimer&#39;s Disease in the Framingham Cohorts</title>
      <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag054076/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag054076/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ag054076&#34;&gt;AG054076&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Framingham Heart Study (FHS) is a prospective, community-based 3-generational study that enrolled participants between ages 20-50 and has examined them every 2-4 years to collect extensive lifestyle, vascular, biomarker data; 9300 have GWAS. Embedded in this cohort are 1036 multigenerational families. Surveillance for AD dementia (and MCI) has been ongoing for over 4 decades. We have identified 1421 incident AD, 1767 MCI, enrolled 800+ in a brain donation program, obtained 7000+ 1.5T brain MRI, and repeated, detailed neuropsychological assessments. We have recently obtained extensive omics in ~6000 (gene expression, methylation, miRNA, metabolomics and proteomics) and genomics (50X whole genome sequences [WGS] in 4197 with pedigree-based imputation to 6554) through the NHLBI funded SABRe CVD (omics) and TOPMed (WGS) programs. We seek to leverage these rich resources (&amp;gt;$25 million). We propose these specific aims: AIM 1 is to examine and explain temporal trends in clinical AD dementia in the FHS cohorts. The age-specific incidence of dementia has declined over the past 4 decades among FHS participants (in press). However, the reasons for this decline remain unclear. We thus propose to continue tracking temporal trends in AD dementia and MCI through intensive surveillance, and verifying diagnoses at autopsy. We hypothesize that better education, treatment of some vascular factors and protective lifestyle changes (diet, activity, social engagement) may partially explain these trends. AIM 2 is to identify the patterns and predictors of preclinical AD within FHS families by obtaining (i) a novel circulating biomarker (plasma tau on 8000+ persons, using samples collected 5-15 years ago and repeat assay in 450) to supplement 1000+ biomarkers already available, and (ii) brain imaging with tau- and amyloid- PET, 3TMRI, including assessment of functional connectivity, tractography and blood flow, in 450 dementia- and stroke-free, FHS participants age 35-75 on whom we have (a) directly verified familial cognition and AD dementia status (both parents and all 4 grandparents were FHS participants), and also (b) have WGS and omics data. AIM 3 is to utilize the available WGS and extensive &amp;lsquo;omics&amp;rsquo; data for deep molecular phenotyping of AD. We will undertake conventional family-based WGS analyses of AD dementia and preclinical AD endophenotypes and novel high dimensional (co-expression, network, systems-based) analyses in collaboration with Drs. DeJager (PI of Accelerated Medicine Partnerships-AD, with omics data in 1200 brains), Witten (award-winning mathematician in applying graphical analysis to omics) and Levy (PI of SABRe-CVD at FHS). We will validate our findings in unrelated and multi-ethnic (Omni) FHS participants, through collaborations with other cohorts, and share all data through dbGaP and BioLINCC for analyses by others. We expect to identify new biologic pathways, drug targets and biomarkers for AD, especially those applicable to the preclinical stage of AD and those explaining promising trends in AD risk; such pathways should prove most useful for AD prevention.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UC Davis Alzheimer&#39;s Disease Center Core</title>
      <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag010129/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag010129/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ag010129&#34;&gt;AG010129&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Administrative Core (AC) is responsible for overall governance and leadership of the UCD ADC as well as spearheading development of new research and initiatives and representing the UCD ADC within and outside the UC Davis community. The landscape of medical research has changed substantially over the last 5 years, challenging the AC to innovate strategic planning so as to optimize utilization of ADC resources to benefit the overall mission of the Center. As a consequence, the AC has developed new avenues of research support and collaboration through state and local partnerships as well as promoting greater philanthropy. The result has been an expanded and highly successful pilot project program, new collaborative research programs, the expansion of career development of diverse faculty that culminated in successful funding of the Latino Aging Research Resource Center, a new and unique Resource Center in Minority Aging Research (RCMAR) that focuses on diversity faculty development and Latino health disparities research. Finally, the AC has worked closely with the UDC School of Medicine (SOM) leadership to expand the reach and impact of UC Davis health care system into the East Bay through the creation of a new clinical facility in Walnut Creek that houses both the East Bay ADC site and an extension of the UCD transplant service. The AC also continues to work closely with Program Officers of the NIA Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Centers program to further the goals of research including expansion of NACC data through MRI analysis as well as emphasizing training and education (including sharing new scientific information with the ADEAR center) in accordance with their scientific and academic mandates.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>US POINTER Neuroimaging Ancillary Study</title>
      <link>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag062689/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davisidealab.github.io/project/ag062689/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ag062689&#34;&gt;AG062689&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. study to PrOtect brain health through lifestyle INTErvention to Reduce risk (U.S. POINTER) is a $35M Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Association-sponsored multisite randomized clinical trial investigating the influence of a multidomain lifestyle intervention (exercise, diet, cognitive stimulation, health coaching for risk factor reduction) on 2yr cognitive trajectories in older adults at increased risk of dementia. POINTER was modeled after Finland&amp;rsquo;s FINGER trial that showed a greater cognitive benefit for those assigned to a multidomain lifestyle intervention group versus health education. POINTER will use a similar two-group study design. The health education (“self-guided”) group will receive information and support through twice yearly group meetings to encourage healthy lifestyle practices. The higher-intensity (“structured”) lifestyle intervention group will receive frequent coaching and group meetings to encourage aerobic exercise and cognitive training 4 days/week, adherence to a modified Mediterranean diet, and cardiovascular risk reduction through increased medical monitoring. Based on the successful FINGER results, the structured group is predicted to show the greatest benefits on 2yr cognitive trajectories given the high intensity of the intervention and the potential for synergistic effects across lifestyle domains. Lacking from the POINTER design, however, are neuroimaging measures to investigate intervention effects on underlying Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease (AD) and cerebrovascular pathophysiology. This proposed imaging ancillary study leverages unique resources provided by the parent trial to examine whether changes in lifestyle can protect brain health and alter AD trajectories. The study will assess these intervention effects on changes in AD and cerebrovascular pathophysiology. It will also examine whether these biomarkers at baseline predict cognitive response to the intervention, which has important implications for precision medicine in identifying those most likely to benefit from this approach. AD and cerebrovascular pathophysiology will be assessed with PET imaging (baseline, 2yrs) to measure beta- amyloid and tau burden, and MR imaging (baseline, 1yr, 2yrs) to measure brain morphometry, white matter hyperintensities and microstructural integrity, and cerebral blood flow. An in-depth analysis of lifestyle changes on disease biomarkers has significant implications for public health given the current weight of evidence showing favorable effects of lifestyle on brain health in older adults that overshadow the results of all other pharmacological treatments to date. Moreover, lifestyle modification is an affordable and accessible approach with health benefits that extend beyond brain health. A critical and clinically relevant feature of the POINTER trial is its recruitment approach which targets a community-based and geographically and racially/ethnically diverse sample, ensuring that the intervention will be applicable to a large proportion of older individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
